Guide to the Causeries du Lundi Records 1880-1996 (bulk 1880-1974) MS 104
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Causeries du Lundi Records
1880-1996 (bulk 1880-1974)
MS 104
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
7.3 Linear feet (18 boxes)
This collection includes member and meeting information of the women's writing group, Causeries du Lundi, founded in 1880 and still active today. Members of this group write and present their essays at meetings, gathering the first Monday of every month in the winter.
Provenance
Donations, 1983, 1990, 1992, 1994, 1996.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Historical Note
The Causeries du Lundi is one the oldest women's literary societies in the U.S. still active today. Elizabeth Hamilton Collum, the granddaughter of Alexander Hamilton, founded the group in 1880 (Anniversary Book, 1930). Collum believed in a "better future for American women than a life of frivolity" and encouraged members to own and express opinions outside of home and social duties and document their interests in art, literature and scholarly culture.
Today, the group meets at a member's home on the first Monday of every winter month. Generally, only one paper per meeting is read, either by the author or another member. As many members come from prominent New York families, the papers provide insight into their family histories as well as old New York, while topics most often include ancestry, art, travel or historical subjects. Causeries du Lundi incorporated in 2008 and is now known as Causeries du Lundi 1880, Inc.
Scope and Content Note
The Causeries du Lundi records are arranged in seven series: President's books, Anniversary books, Annual Reports, Minutes, Member's Essays and Invitations. The bulk of the records are from 1880 to 1974. The majority of the collection consists of the essays written by Causerie members.
The collection documents the founding and administration of the group, its membership, and papers presented by the Causeries du Lundi. The Rules of Government state protocol and procedures of joining and maintaining membership in the Causeries du Lundi.The President's Books detail membership listings, addresses, schedules, and paper topics. Anniversary books were published in celebration of the passing of the years and provide history of the organization and its members. Annual reports and Minutes detail meeting and hostess information, with synopses of presented papers and ensuing discussion, as well as treasury reports. Member files are arranged alphabetically and contain the essays of the members. Some files may also contain clippings, comments and correspondence relating to the essays.
The Causeries du Lundi records contain many essays by women of prominent New York backgrounds with last names such as Lefferts, Peabody, Roosevelt, Delano, Erving, Pierrepont and Parsons, to name a few. One paper of historical interest was submitted by Mrs. Edward Curtis, whose husband performed Abraham Lincoln's autopsy. She included an article written by her husband in 1926 about the event.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged within the following seven series:
Series I. Rules of Government, 1922, 1947, 1970
Series II. President's books, 1926-1979
Series III. Anniversary books, 1890-1955
Series IV. Annual reports, 1897-1901
Series V. Minutes, 1880-1974
Series VI. Members' Essays, 1887-1995
Series VII. Invitations, 1930-1980
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Further material about the Causeries du Lundi is located at the New-York Historical Society within the
Erving-King Papers.
Book Clubs (Discussion groups) -- New York (State) -- New York; New York (N.Y.) -- Clubs; Societies; Women -- Societies and clubs; Women History
- Series I. Rules of Government, 1922, 1947, 1970
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes printed material detailing the protocol of membership and governing committees in the Causeries du Lundi.
  - Rules of Government, 1922, 1947, 1970, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II. President's books, 1926-1979
  President's books contain membership information as well as meeting schedules, including the hostess and paper topic lists.
  - President's Books, 1926-1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - President's Books, 1944-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series III. Anniversary books, 1890-1955
  This series contains printed books celebrating the anniversaries of and detailing the history of the organization and its members.
  - Anniversary Book, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anniversary Book, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anniversary Book, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anniversary Book, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anniversary Book, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series IV. Annual reports, 1897-1901
  Annual reports contain meeting and budget information. After 1901, annual reports are kept with the meeting minutes.
  - Annual Report, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series V. Minutes, 1880-1974
  Minutes detail meeting and hostess information, with synopses of presented papers and ensuing discussion, as well as the group's treasury reports. Book numbers are taken from the cover of notebook or binder of the minutes. Many have been removed from their binder for preservation purposes, but a representative sample of the binders is available at the end of the series.
  - Minutes (Book 1), 1880 Apr.-1886 Jan. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Minutes (Book 2), 1886 Feb.-1889 Jan. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Minutes (Book 3), 1889 Jan.-1891 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes (Book 4), 1892 Jan.-1894 May (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minutes (Book 5), 1894 Nov.-1896 Apr. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Minutes (Book 6), 1896 Nov.-1900 Feb. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Minutes (Book 7), 1900 Mar.-1902 Mar. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Minutes (Book 8), 1902 Nov.-1905 Jan. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Minutes (Book 9), 1905 Feb.-1907 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Minutes (Book 10), 1907 Nov.-1909 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes (Book 10A), 1910 Nov.-1911 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Minutes (Book 11), 1909 Nov.-1912 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Minutes (Book 12), 1912 Nov.-1914 Apr. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Minutes (Book 13), 1914 Dec.-1917 Apr. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Minutes (Book 14), 1917 Dec.-1920 Apr. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Minutes (Book 15), 1920 Dec.-1926 Apr. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Minutes (Book 16), 1926 Dec.-1929 Apr. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Minutes (Book 17), 1929 Dec.-1933 Apr. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Minutes (Book 18), 1933 Dec.-1934 Apr. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Minutes (Book 19), 1934 Dec.-1940 Apr. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1936 Dec.-1941 Nov. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Minutes (Book 20), 1940 Nov.-1941 Apr. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Minutes (Book 21), 1941 Dec.-1944 Apr. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Minutes (Book 22), 1944 May-1952 Apr. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Minutes (Book 23), 1952 Apr.-1957 Mar. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1957 Apr.-1959 Apr. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1959 Nov.-1963 Apr. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1963 Nov.-1967 May (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1967 Dec.-1970 Apr. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1970 Apr.-1974 Jan. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Representative sample of Minutes binder, 1934-1940 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series VI. Members' Essays
  This series contains members' essay files with corresponding dates. There is a chronological list of all papers at the beginning of the series. Most papers are 10-30 pages in length, most having been transcribed and typewritten and usually pertain to art, ancestral or historical topics. Some files contain clippings and other miscellaneous notes. If there are more than four papers in a file, the range of dates is given. Member's files are arranged alphabetically and are arranged as their names appear in their papers.
  - Chronological list of papers, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Wolcott Erskine Andrews, 1975, 1977, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. William Appleton Aiken, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. Thompson Barker, 1959, 1964, 1968, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. Philip Bartlett, 1961-1994 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Mrs. Henry Bartol (Hester G.), 1917-1956 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. E. Farrar Bateson (Rosina O.), 1954, 1959, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. William Massena Benjamin, 1947, 1952, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Mrs. Frank Berry, 1963, 1967, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. Hans Bielenstein (Gabrielle Maupin), 1983, 1985, 1988, 1995, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Mrs. Christina F. Boardman, 1942-1967 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Martin Bregman (Cornelia Sharpe), 1998 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Caroline L. Brown, 2012 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Louise Bruce, 2005-2006 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. Julian Buckley, 1964, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Mrs. H. Schuyler Cammann (Katherine), 1928, 1930, 1965, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. George Canfield, 1927, 1930, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Angela Cason, 2011 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Miss Barbara Cheney, 1932-1970 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. George Cheney, 1927, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Mrs. B. Clarkson, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Gloria J. Conn, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Mrs. Thomas Riggs Cox (Marian Buckley), 1963, 1965, 1968, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Mrs. George Crocker (Elizabeth), 1935 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Miss Constance Curtis, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Mrs. Edward Curtis (Augusta L.), 1907, 1912, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Miss Olga Dahlgren, 1947-1964 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Pamela Tiffin Danon, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. Henry W de Forest, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. Joseph L. Delafield (Mary R.), 1948, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - G.M. Dexter, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Miss Alys M. Downing, 1945-1967 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Augustus Downing, 1937-1962 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Mrs. Joseph Drexel (Lucy Wharton), 1887 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. Alfred Edey, 1935, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Mrs. W. Page Ely, 1928-1948 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Miss Justine Bayard Erving, 1918-1952 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Guy Ewall, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Firth Haring Fabend, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. B. Tappan Fairchild (Julia Freeman), 1955-1977 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Eleanor V.R. Fairfax, 1910 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Mrs. Peter Farnum (Louise Kobbe), 1941, 1945, 1949, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. Ernest Flagg, 1938-1969 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Wynne Byard Fooshee, 1987, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Mrs. William Forsyth (Agnes M.), 1984, 1989, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. Guernsey Frey (Josephine W.), 1958, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Mrs. John A. Gade, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Mrs. William Montague Geer, Jr. (Edith), 1927 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Mrs. J. Roosevelt Geer (Dorothy), 1941-1961 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Mrs. Langdon Geer, 1937, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Miss Edna Grant, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Miss Julia M. Grant, 1949-1961 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Martha Hughes Griffis, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Miss Frances Grimes, 1946, 1950, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Mrs. Augustus Hand, 1931-1956 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. Sinclair Hatch (Laura Lea), 1961, 1964, 1970, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Harter, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Mrs. Geoffrey Hellman (Katherine), 1971-1979 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. Seton Henry (Josephine W. Drexel), 1942-1958 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Mrs. G.P. Herrick, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Mrs. C. Lambery Heyniger, 1928, 1935, 1939, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Arthur B. Hoff, 1974, 1977, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Hoge, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - S.C.W. Hoppin, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Sarah Lord Howells, 1893 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Mrs. Theodore Humphrey, 1936, 1940, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Miss Catherine Huntington, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Frances Huntington (Susan L.), 1933, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Mrs. Robert S. Hutchins (Evelyn), 1968-1984 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. M. Hutchinson (Martha), 1935 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Mrs. John H. Janeway, 1910-1931 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Mrs. Edwin Jarrett, 1949, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Elbrun Kimmelman, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Mrs. Augustus King, 1939, 1945, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Mrs. Adrian Lambert, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Mrs. Elliott Hugh Lee, 1959, 1964, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Mrs. Barent Lefferts (Isabella M.), 1935-1955 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Gillett Lefferts, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Howard Lipson, 1970, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Miss Alice Lounsberry, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. John T. McClintock (Mary M.), 1972-1989 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Mrs. Dennis Daughtry McCrary (Eugenia), 1986, 1988, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Renee McKay, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Alan D. McLean, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Mrs. Malone, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Lynn S. Manger, 2009 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Julia O. Marrow, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Charlotte Delafield Marsh, 1927 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Mrs. Francis Robert Masters, 1940, 1948, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Mrs. Richard Meade (Helena Rutherford Ely), 1908-1965 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Mrs. John Melcher (Helen), 1938-1968 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Mrs. John Williams Morgan, 1955, 1958, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. S.C. Munroe, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Joseph Lawrence Myers (Henrietta), 1927, 1932 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Susan Nagel, 1999-2012 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Acosta Nichols, 1979, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Miss Jeannette Olyphant, 1956, 1959, 1963, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. Leonard E. Opdycke, 1911 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Ostrander, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Mrs. Augustus G. Paine (Francisca Warren), 1939, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. Hugh E. Paine, Jr. (Julia), 1970, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Elinor Parker, 1983, 1986, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Mrs. Williams Parsons (Louise B.), 1976, 1978, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Mrs. Henry S. Patterson, undated (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Mrs. George R. Peabody, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Mrs. John D. Peabody, 1945 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Mrs. Robert Swain Peabody (Helen Lee), 1944-1972 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Mitzi Perdue, 2011-2012 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Madelaine Piel, 2011 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Mrs. William Curtis Pierce (Elizabeth Gay), 1965-1987 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Miss Mary Cheney Platt, 1969, 1971, 1977, undated (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Mrs. George Poindexter, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Mrs. Frank Porter, 1959, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Mrs. John A. Pruyn (LaVerne), 1972-1991 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Harold Pulsifer (Susan Nichols), 1931, 1936, 1940, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Hopeton D. Atterbury Quaid, 1953, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. Henry Rawle, undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. Charles A. Richards (Henrietta King), 1927, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Cordelia C. Richards, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. Beverly R. Robinson, 1963, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Philip Ashton Rollins, 1932, 1937, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Kate Shippen Roosevelt, 1920, 1922, 1924 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. James Rorimer (Katherine), 1988, 1990, 1992, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Joan T. Rosasco, 2011, 2012 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Mrs. Frances J. Rue, Jr., 1968, 1982, 1984, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Mrs. Ralph Saltus (Marilyn M.) (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Mrs. James C. Sargent (Rebecca P.J.), 1974-1995 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Mrs. Theodore Fiske Savage (May), 1950-1972 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. William L. Savage (Serena Hand), 1932-1944 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Schuyler Schieffelin, 1934 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Miss Alice Seward, 1911 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. Sherman, 1939 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Miss Shippen, 1945, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. Minot Simons, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Slade, 1941, 1943, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Mary (Polly) Coxe Smith, 1990, 2001, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. Mason Smith (Mary A. E.), 1949, 1951, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Mrs. H. Southworth, 1966, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Mrs. T. Guthrie Spears, Jr. (Susan Savage), 1954-1978 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Mrs. Henry A. Stickney (Helen Morgan Frick), 1938, 1941, 1943, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Mrs. Ernest Stillman (Mildred W.), 1943, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Eugenia Stillman, 1985 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Lloyd Paul Stryker, 1957, 1961 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. Arthur Sutcliffe (Alice Crary), 1927-1951 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. Arthur Talbot, 1930, 1939 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Mrs. J.H. Thomas, 1944, 1948, 1952 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. Elliot Tuckerman, 1927 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Miss E. L. Tuckerman, 1922 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Miss Jane Tuckerman, 1903-1914 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. Twiss, 1967, 1972, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Mrs. Twyeffort, 1979, 1982, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Unknown Authors, undated (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Gwendolen Van Antwerp, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Mrs. John King Van Rensselaer, undated (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Miss Mary Wagstaff, 1930-1967 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Mrs. Bradford Warner, 1989 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Mrs. Wolcott Warner (Eloise), 1995 (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Martha Rosalie Myer Webber, 1958-1976 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Miss Alice Delano Weekes, 1926, 1929, 1933 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Wightman (Anne), 1943, 1946 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Mary Jane Victor Wheelock, 1999 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. W. Hollingsworth Whyte (Jenny Bell), 1974, 1978, 1987, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Anne H. Willard, 1955 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. I.T. Williams (Edna D.), 1969,1970, 1975 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Roderick Williams (Dorothea C.), 1978-2003 (Box 18, Folder 8, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. Charles Woodman, 1957, 1964, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Alice Bradford Woolsey, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Benjamin S. Young, 1940-1972 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. Thomas S. Young (Caroline E.), 1905, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Series VII. Invitations
  This series consists of ten printed invitations to Causeries du Lundi meetings.
  - Invitations, 1930-1980 (Box 19, Folder 5)